all right so welcome everyone to another
awakening from the meaning crisis q a
our guest today is jp marceau
who is the editor-in-chief of jonathan
pajot's symbolic world blog
thank you jp for being here today
thanks for the invitation guys yeah so
so so you you got involved with uh
you're involved so so you're involved
with jonathan's uh
symbolic world maybe you could tell us a
little bit about yourself
how you got interested in in symbology
you know how how you met john and and
how you got into all of this
yeah sure um what happened the initial
story is fairly
typical of a lot of uh people in
in in the west and was raised in a
catholic household
i got away from it during my high school
years as i
became more scientistic i would say
um got interested in in philosophy to
try and
find out meaning could possibly fit into
my scientistic
worldview so uh i eventually
got away uh from scientism
went into psychism more precisely
because i thought it offered
the best um stepping point
away from materialism and scientism
and in the course of doing this uh i was
studying uh at a doing a master's in
philosophy to try and approach uh
these these questions more precisely and
it was around the time when
uh jordan peterson and jonathan pedro
and also general ricky started to
come into the scene so this would be
like uh late in 2016 i think
and at first i didn't really understand
what uh jonathan was
was saying really and i added even
trouble
understanding how what john christian
was saying could be
real in a mid physical metaphysical
sense oh it wasn't just psychology but
anyways i was sort of working with
uh all of that stuff and
eventually uh when jonathan started his
patreon
i started to to support him uh and i had
a chance to have a few
phone calls uh with him fairly early on
so i asked him
you know what to talk told him uh talk
to him a bit
about the research i was doing in my
master's
on in philosophy of mine especially in
psychism and you're trying to
see how it could possibly bridge with a
sort of symbolic worldview
i was interested to to see how
his symbolical view was getting at
something real
how it wasn't is it just studying
patterns
in our minds how it wasn't just telling
it about the structures of
human consciousness but how it was
talking to us about
the the actual nature of the
of the world of reality and so
over time i got a clear understanding of
what metaphysics
would make a symbol equal view possible
and as i was doing this i was also
trying to use the symbolical view to
solve some
some issues uh a really cool one that i
dealt with with jonathan was
the zombie problem you know both john
and jonathan have done
great work on that front to lay out how
it is that
the zombie is a symbol of nihilism it's
a
a symbol of you know you can sit as
creatures that are
cut off from from meaning that are have
only the
samuel crumbs of of meaning
you know they are sort of a community
but they don't talk with one another
they don't have profound meaning
making with one another they just sort
of follow the same group as a
mindless herd they uh don't even have
speech like the capacity for logos they
don't have that
they uh they have our brains like the
very organ that
uh we use to to mediate between meaning
and matter so there are a lot of
reasons why zombies are a
are a good symbol for nihilism
and then uh i wanted to know no in
addition to
let's say that solving philosophically
the problems of nihilism
or even addressing them practically um
with
let's say the sort of practices that
john has been talking about
developing communities and uh practices
to fight nihilism and demeaning crisis i
also wanted to know with jonathan
what would be a symbolic solution to the
zombie problem
like within without having to get into
philosophy or
even practices like within a symbolical
view what would be
a a solution to the zombie problem
and this was relevant to me because as i
was working through this
in the case of my studies i was having
recurrent
zombie nightmares um which you see it is
that
as i was processing during the daytime
you know the arguments for nihilism and
trying to to get away
from it i was also sort of wrestling
with the same issues symbolically at
night
uh i was having just recurring
nightmares about the zombie apocalypse
there was always a zombie apocalypse
in my dreams just just never ending i
would just at some point i would die and
then i would wake up
uh from my dreams and then i would just
go back to another zombie nightmare it
was it wasn't as bad as it seems
actually because
at some point you just get used to it
and i sort of knew that i would just
resurrect and start over so it's not as
bad
as it sounds but i was still curious to
see what i could possibly do to uh
to solve that problem and actually my
studies
really helped uh you know with by going
from materialism
to pensanchism my zombie nightmares were
already cut off quite a bit because
it's you can see it as you're infusing
consciousness back into zombies
instead of having just material
creatures that follow the
laws of physics or whatever you you put
consciousness
back into that you put emotions
sensations and so on into the zombies so
it's already an improvement over
the zombie crisis uh over the the
meaning crisis
so this was already cut off my
nightmares and then looked into ethics
and
was fairly convinced by people like
jonathan hyde
and also uh saint thomas aquinas who
have
good theories about ethics about how it
could relate
to to the world so in addition to having
consciousness back into my worldview
uh and fighting the zombies that way i
was also reinserting
morality vices and virtues in my old
view so
you know this again cut off the zombie
nightmares but it wasn't completely cut
off but
in in discussing the problem
symbolically with jonathan
we found the solution of uh it's
basically
the christian solution because you can
see zombies also as just a perversion of
the
christian story i think both john and
jonathan have said this
um you know instead of having a
resurrection as christianity claims of
the dead who come back with glorious
bodies will come back like fully alive
you you come back with but without
meaning in the case of zombies and
the symbolic solution within the
christian worldview is
to not only build meaning uh not only
build meaningful civilization but
to actually do what christ would do to
give your life over to say try and save
everyone so even
even the zombies and as we as jonathan
and i
discussed this and found this symbolic
solution uh my
zombie nightmares completely went away
so that was interesting
made me take symbolism a bit more
seriously and over time i kept uh
in touch with jonathan we met as i once
met at his uh his parish
he met me once also rece just before
cover actually at my parish and
we still talk often uh as in a um
a webinar for is a some of his top-level
patrons
so that's how i i got in touch with with
jonathan and recently we started the
symbolic world blog
to try to create a
a community where we explore symbolism
and try to develop that worldview
so that's on the side of jonathan and
with john
it actually comes from a a discussion i
had with paul vander clay
about a year ago now um because i had
been following john's work for a while
at some point i think maybe in 2016 or
2017 uh
jordan peterson had tweeted about uh
john's
john's work the fact that john put out
some lectures online
uh it was the thing those were
the buddhism and cognitive science
lecture series
and i had quite liked those i was i
actually used them
when i was doing a course on a
phenomenology uh for my masters
so uh yeah i was a bit familiar with
john's work
and i knew that uh polymeric was gonna
talk to john so
i i mentioned you know john
uh john's work when talking with with
paul and
uh proposed you know penn psychism
as at least the first step to address
the meaning crisis and you know
john uh heard about this and we ended up
having a discussion about
it and it was a really cool discussion
uh we both learned from it so we ended
up having several others i think by now
we've spoken like
five or six times and uh we're still
gonna
have discussions in the future i think
we've
mostly been discussing metaphysics and
especially
uh the place of christianity and the
neoplatonism
so that's uh how i i've been uh
in contact with
great so sorry strong can you can you
mute
uh so
all right sorry i'm gonna i'm gonna try
sorry got some static there
uh okay so so so you talked about
whether there's a lot of things you
talked about so you talked about
the symbolic world view what is a
symbolic world view
yeah um the way i like to put it is
a symbolical view is a world view where
you try to explore
the the the relationships between
the different levels of being so
i think it's best to give examples when
we do this
an example i like to use all the time is
uh
the symbol of the head like as in a head
over a body
if you just think about your head your
head is a symbol of
of your mind and it mediates between
your body
and your mind and we don't have to get
into the precise metaphysics of what is
the exact relationship between mind and
matter
the point is just that when uh
you can take your different members you
know you have ends you have eyes and so
on
spread over space and time uh do all
kinds of concrete things
and somehow all of the information that
uh
it's uh your ears your your retina
your your hands and so on they're
gathered up
into your uh they're gathered by your
head
and somehow they will uh become
abstracted
in two conscious into uh conscious
patterns
so we can take the example of uh as i um
you know i urge you talk brett tons of
stuff occurred over my my eardrums tons
of vibrations
uh then they got routed up to my
my through my brain and there
something happens we don't have to get
into the precise metaphysics but somehow
these uh meaningless oscillations on my
ear
somehow they uh they became
related to my consciousness to a pattern
i heard words and sentences
so we have you know an abstract pattern
of a sentence
that became abstracted from the concrete
level of my physical being
and conversely when i speak as i speak
these words for instance i'm taking
abstract patterns in my
my mind i'm taking sentences with with
words with meanings and so on
and i'm unfolding this through my
my mouth through my lungs into
concrete uh oscillations in space and
time so my
my mouth and my lungs will move
in very complex ways that look
meaningless at that scale at the scales
of just new
uh waves uh over the air
but what is at this physical level just
uh oscillations and activities in my uh
my cells
is actually a manifestation of
the the more abstract pattern in my mind
so
to come back exclusively to symbolism
symbolism is the study
of mediators between levels of being
such as what i just went through my my
head
is a symbol that media is between my
physical layer
between my my the cells in my eardrums
and the cells in over my mouth and
in my lungs the end media is between
those cells
those concrete cells in space and time
and the abstract pattern
in my my consciousness and symbolism is
about studying
those jumps those uh those symbols that
mediate between levels of being at all
levels so uh
this works at you can look at it at
lower levels what i just said about my
head and my body is also true
if you look at what happens
in a cell for instance in in a cell you
have tons of different organelles that
are spread over
space and time uh doing all kinds of
chemical interactions very quickly
that can be meaningfully gathered in uh
when they reach a nucleus into
information
they will be gathered up into genetic
information so what was
just let's say the mitochondria is
having a certain issue
and they release certain enzymes
eventually those enzymes will have
complex uh relationships with the
nucleus
where the nucleus will will gather these
seemingly meaningless enzymes
and it will gather dip into information
genetic and form into the genetic
information of the the nucleus
and then this will let's say react by uh
creating
certain other enzymes to fix whatever
was going wrong with the
the mitochondria so you have a physical
artifact the nucleus that mediates
between
the physical layer of the chemicals in
the cell and
the abstract genetic information of the
cell the whole pattern of the cell so
the cell holds together
because uh the the nucleus provides a
certain pattern
that he can then that he can then it can
then mediate
through uh to the different organelles
in the cell so the way you see it is
that
the organelles provide matter for the
patterns
uh of the the cell and the patterns of
the cell keep the the different
materials
of the the organelles together so that
what
the relationship that holds between my
physical layer
and the layer of my consciousness is
analogous to what happens at other
levels of being such as what happens in
the cell where you can see
the the what my head does to my body is
sort of what the nucleus does
for the organelles and we could also
look at higher levels of being
uh the same thing happens in a a church
for instance or
just in a community we can take even uh
this uh
this recording right now you can see
that brett
brett is a mediator between the
the community as a whole and it's even
individual members you know rather than
having just
let's say we're 15 people in this chat
rather than having 15 people
doing their own separate thing all over
the place we're gathered up into
a community uh by brett who you know
invited me and then if i invited all of
you guys
so that today we enact the pattern of
the community where we
get together we speak uh certain things
we we type words
into a certain chat and this makes us a
group
and a group is an abstract entity when
you think about it's uh
it's it has yeah it exists at a higher
level than just the individuals
but you know it's a real thing we really
are behaving as a group
right now and in the same way that my
head be immediate between my
consciousness
and my body well you can see that is
mediating
between the community that exists as a
as a whole
and the individual members so symbolism
to conclude is the the study of
the symbols that mediate between those
uh those layers of being
and how how would you differentiate
between a symbol and
an analogy or a metaphor
that's a that's a good question
well how would you define for instance a
an analogy or a metaphor
i mean i i tend to think of you know a
metaphor
as something that you're describing
in a way that that evokes the thing
you're describing but is not the thing
you're describing
okay yeah i think the the difference
will have to do with participation
um let's say if i take
my if i take my head for instance
my head really does participate
in my in in
in my mind and my body it uh it is a
member like my other members
but it also participates uh in my mind
and i'm not sure that the same would be
true of metaphors
or analogies um
for instance if i take
so what metaphor did you use as an
example yet already
oh uh
i i don't think i i did you i mean the
meta okay you know like like
like or or captaining a ship you know
going through the
going through the waters you know could
be could be a metaphor
yeah well yeah i'm not sure hm
it's i don't think it's that different
uh
so captain captaining a ship
yeah i mean it's an expression i don't
know how
not sure it's a let's take another
example
um because i'm not sure it's even really
a metaphor
i think it's just the expression maybe
it's because i'm not familiar enough
with the english language but
isn't this what captain means exactly to
to be the leader of a ship it's like
being the head of the ship and
no it's it's true that the captain is
the end of the ship um
so in that case i would tend to
oh yeah go ahead sorry i think the
metaphor would be that that brett is
captaining the ship of discord
okay right okay yeah yeah
okay well then i guess you could say
that
an analogies or metaphors or things that
you use
to to get at symbols
uh so let's see the the idea that brett
is
is captaining the ship of discord is you
use a certain
image you use a certain uh perceptual
machinery that we have of you know
we can we can deal we can recognize the
captain and the ship
and we have perceptual machinery to
recognize this
to get at the pattern of a captain over
his ship
and we we can use this metaphor to map
it onto
uh let's say the case of bread and the
discord
and this allows us to get at uh the
yeah really the symbolism the fact that
in both cases you have the
the captain of the ship is the other
with the ship and the
and brett is the the head of the the
discord so
maybe a way of seeing it is that whether
you use metaphors or analogies
they will work because they will work
when they get at
symbols that are analogous between those
different layers of being
so yeah does that answer the question
yeah yeah yes so so i i want to talk
about this
so you wrote a blog post uh recently uh
about
the burning of cell towers and you were
discussing it with john
and yeah so so you were just describing
the symbolism of the cell towers
uh as representing you know the covid
crisis and in their role in
in in uh allowing people to move
uh you know keeping people more docile
and
and and just just you you identify just
a variety of different
ways in which in which the cell tower is
a symbol of kovid
and and you talked about the people
burning down cell towers uh but blaming
it on 5g
on the physical and you noted that that
you thought these people were keying
into the symbol
even if they did if it didn't occur to
them in the first place
and yeah and so i guess mike
i have a few questions on this but you
know you almost seem to be
describing an objectivity to symbols
do you think symbols are objective that
that they they arise objectively or
are they a part of our own minds our own
interpretations
of of various things that's a that's a
good question
the word uh objectivity is fraught with
all kinds of uh
of debates in in philosophy but let me
say that
i do think that symbols are real and
that they're not just a
um let's say fabrications
of our mind i do think that the fact
that let's say
the nucleus mediates between the genetic
information
and the organelles is is real i think it
i think it exists i think
the the nucleus really does mediate
between those two
i think that your your ad really is a
symbol
of uh of of yourself that it really made
the edge between your body
and your mind uh so i
i don't think we're projecting this uh i
think we're really getting at
that something that actually you know
holds the world together there really is
a unity between
the organelles in the cell and its
genetic information
so i think we're getting at something
real when we talk about
the nucleus as a symbol for the for the
cell
and similarly there really is uh
a relationship between your mind and
your body we don't have to even get into
the precise metaphysics but
definitely the ed as a role uh
as an important role in this it's not
just a a
fabrication uh we really are getting at
something real
so so can somebody be right or wrong in
how they interpret a symbol
yeah yeah yeah you can uh if
if you try to identify something that
isn't
really mediating between those layers as
you say it is then then you're wrong
um for instance in the case of the
the cell towers maybe the people who
so okay so people have a good intuition
to start off from
you know the intuit that sat ours did
play some role
in the kovit crisis and as you said i
mentioned a few i
don't think it's necessary to go over
all of them now but let's see
some towers allow the government to
communicate and uh send information to
us they allow people to panic on social
media
and to hunker down so sat towers did
participate they did mediate between the
social layer
and the they didn't mediate between a
social level panic
and uh the the physical world
so if they are a physical artifact in a
physical world that also
uh has a social import that play the
role within the social
panic so they're simple because the
immediate between the social layer and
the physical layer
but if you say that uh they do so
at the physical level that they do so
because uh
the way they immediate between the the
kobe crisis
and the and the physical level
is by is because 5g technology causes
the coronavirus
uh or makes it worse somehow then you're
i think you're misidentifying
this the symbolism that is going on so
the cell towers really do mediate
between
the crisis and the physical layer but
you can misidentify the way in which
they do so by claiming for instance that
it's all just a physical thing
and not rather a social phenomenon
now so do you think symbols can be
created or are they discovered or both
that's a good question um
let's say we can try to think even about
let's see
the world before there was any
any cell like before any sort of life
there's a sense in which the the pattern
of
let's say a a human liver cell
this pattern already existed in the
abstract it was simply not
manifest yet uh it it became manifest
when sales first appeared um
so i think it's i think that's a that's
a start
when we get to the human level i think
we can get
at um we can discover good symbols
yeah i think it's much more of a
discovery any creation if you
try to to create a symbol maybe uh you
maybe the first person who uh
if you can try to think of a well i can
just even
take can take churches for instance or
uh any building that holds people
together
okay so the church mediates between a
community
and its individual members so in that
sense you know people created it
the first there was a time when there
was no church and there was a church
uh but it's not that people
created the pattern and then from then
on it
uh like it was
from then on it it existed i think it's
more that the pattern
the abstract pattern already existed and
then it became
manifest when people actually built
churches
um another way to see it maybe is uh
in case of i think i think it's similar
to a bunch of other debates in
philosophy having to do with the
the reality of certain entities i think
the same thing with mathematics for
instance
uh in the recent decades people have
been
creating uh you can see people have been
discovering
all kinds of theorems and mathematics
that you know weren't known before
but we're able to create all all kinds
of crazy machines with them
like the we can build atomic bombs which
is a new thing
and which allowed certain mathematics to
manifest themselves for the first time
in human history
but it's not like those patterns
wouldn't have existed without human
beings to discover them
they were already real they were simply
not manifested yet
so so so so we're here in the
you know in this forum where we're we're
trying to sort of
talk about the religion that's not a
religion are you familiar with john's
concept of that
yeah yeah yeah so so so one thing you
know we're interested in is
is you know what what symbols would
would be representative of the religion
that's not a religion so
what should we be thinking about as
we're trying to identify
identify sort of maybe even new symbols
uh
to to identif you know to associate with
with this movement
yeah that's a great question
yeah because as i said i think we we
we have to tap into patterns that
already
exist we don't really create
symbols i think so i would i would i
think you're already doing this you know
if you
study the symbols that have been
effective
in other systems uh it will tell you
about how to mediate between those
different layers
for instance if you study the way in
which
certain communities can come together
around around the symbol of a church
how different people can become an
actual community
you know into when they come into a
building and they do certain things
this will help you understand how you
can so
craft your own symbols how you can
find those those ways
to map between the community
and uh the individuals so that's all i
could
really uh say symbolism is
it's something you have to practice uh
and with this practice you get better at
spotting symbols
uh and spotting also symbols that emerge
for instance the idea that uh you know
cell towers
uh cause or somehow make the coronavirus
worse
is a symbol that that emerged and people
who
burned down towers don't seem really
conscious of what their
of the symbolism of what they're doing
exactly but it's still something that
emerged
but and if you practice you know seeing
the world symbolically
you'll be able to identify those
patterns that uh
that emerge and you'll be able to foster
the ones that are useful
so maybe you'll see let's see in the
case of this discord uh if you see that
this discord is holding people together
right graphing bringing them into a
community that
unites people you can see that then this
discord is a symbol uh of uh
the symbolism uh sorry of the religion
that's not a religion you know it's
it's bringing different people into the
religion that's not a religion
so you can try to spot this and foster
this i think
more than anything it's a symbolism it's
a practice where you have to
get better and better at identifying the
symbols that emerge
and fostering the ones that that uh that
that work best
all right thank you so much we i want to
move to question now we have a couple
questions on pan psychism so
could you just before we get to the
questions could you tell us
what is pan psychism
it's like somebody's a it's a theory in
philosophy of mind
that has been gaining a lot of steam in
the last uh three decades
i would say the
it was also pretty popular about 100
years ago but the reason why it's coming
back is
that there it's it's a neat way
to get over the faults of materialism
so most penn psychists will argue that
first
materialism does not explain
consciousness it does not explain
phenomenal experiments for instance
the the the blue of my desk is not
something
that i can get at if i just look at
matter as physics as physical science
describes it
this this problem has been formulated
very well by david chalmers
uh about 25 years ago made it really
clear in his book especially
the the conscious mind and i
if you want to i can go over some of the
arguments later but i think i'd rather
go over that uh quickly and get to
pennsylkisson
the just the basic idea is that more and
more people
or more people agree that
the the world as described by physical
science
doesn't allow you to talk about your
consciousness doesn't allow you to talk
about
phenomenal experience like the blue that
you see the pain that you feel
the the emotions that that you feel and
so on
and the solution and the solution that
has been gaining steam
is pensanquism which it solves the
problem
in a very elegant way um there are a few
arguments for this i'm going to try to
give just the main one
that explains pan psychism uh well at
the same time as it argues for it
if you look at the entities described by
physical science
you never actually get to the nature
of those entities you only ever get how
those entities behave
if you take an electron for instance
physical science can tell you
how the electron behaves like it can
give you laws
that describe how the electron interacts
with other electrons with protons and so
on
but it doesn't tell you why the electron
does this never tells you the intrinsic
nature
of the electron even let's say the fact
that physical sense gives you the the
mass and the charge
of the electron it still doesn't really
tell you the nature of the electron
because
saying that the electron has this mass
and that charge only
tells you that if you plug this mass or
that charge into that equation you'll
get that output
so symbolism only ever sorry
physical science only ever gives you the
behavior of things
and doesn't give you their nature so
that that's the one side of things
and now the the
the clever insight of penn psychism is
to try to
feel that ontological void in physics
by putting consciousness in there and
you actually start by doing this at the
human level
if i look at bread for instance
i can look at bread at the purely
physical level if i want to i can
say that okay well brett is a very
complex set of fundamental particles
uh and i can use the laws of physics to
predict what
brett will do he will behave in such in
such a way uh
he will uh i can even predict maybe that
at three o'clock eastern time you will
get into the discord server and uh start
the conversation with a
jp and uh a bunch of uh john ricky
enthusiasts
maybe i can explain this
physicalistically but it's only really a
superficial explanation it's only in
terms
it only explains breath behavior in
terms of the behavior of more
fundamental particles doesn't give you
the intrinsic reason for any of those
things doesn't give you the intrinsic
nature of breath or the intrinsic nature
of is uh
is fundamental particles so the inside
of pan psychism is that
but we actually do have a great
candidate for
the the the intrinsic nature of breath
or for is uh for the
the real reasons of his actions namely
is consciousness it was because of his
desire
to have this conversation here that
brett
logged into the discord at the three
o'clock eastern time
so you identify the intrinsic nature of
breaths uh of brett's body
with his consciousness and you the trick
in pansenchism is to do the exact same
thing at
all the different layers of the physical
ontology so
the reason why cells behave the way they
do
is well because they have a certain
conscious nature the reason why
molecules behave the way they do it
because they have a certain
conscious nature the reason why
fundamental particles behave the way
they do
it's because they have a certain uh
conscious nature and then
depends like the the trick in
pennsylvania is to try and study
the how is it that let's say my
consciousness can be the combination of
smaller consciousnesses uh but
the reason why this is convincing to a
lot of people right now is that it
allows you to keep
your materialist ontology whole
wholesale
you can still say that okay electrons
really do exist so these cells
cells molecules and humans and so on you
can you can keep your materialistic
ontology
but you add consciousness in there and
this allows you to kill two pers with
one stone
you can fill the ontological void of
physics at the same time as you explain
the art problem of consciousness at the
same time as you give a place for
consciousness in nature
so that's why uh so that's the basic
idea for pakistan and that's also why
it's been
popular in the recent decades all right
thank you so with that let's turn to
skyler who has who has a question
are you there skylar i think he's typing
oh he wants me to read it oh please
right
yeah and just around if you want me to
read it please please
ask me uh at the top to read it so
his question would you please steal man
the critiques you have heard of your pan
psychist
perspectives and also provide insight on
what it is you gain from this point of
view
i love the fractal patterns of masculine
feminine dark light
silent sound that you seem to be
immersed in i hope that this may
help frame why it is we could use you in
these conversations
thank you also for the cell burning cell
tower burning videos
very helpful yeah a good question
the best critique of uh penn psychism
comes from
james from william james
it's the combination problem uh how is
it that
different consciousnesses can combine
because this is at the heart of
of pansysm if you really want to claim
that human consciousness is a
combination of let's say the
consciousnesses of
human cells then you need to give an
account of how it is that
different consciousnesses can combine
and
this is widely recognized as the most
important problem
for uh psychism and
it's not clear that even if you stay
within let's say
modern analytical philosophy of mind
there doesn't seem to be really great
solutions to this
but what has happened uh i think this
answers your second question like
how can this provide insight on what it
is that i gained from this point of view
is in trying to address the combination
problem
as it is uh expressed in modern analytic
philosophy of mind
i had to look backwards in time to
authors who give i think good answers to
this
um and it ended up ended up bringing me
closer and closer to
neoplatonism to to make a long story
short
like the the relationship between the
one and the many
within panasonicism about many
consciousnesses can be united in one
consciousnesses it's sort of the same
problem as what philosophers have been
dealing with
since since maybe plato of how it is
that different things
can somehow be worn and it's something
that
has been yeah it's something that has
become clearer in the course of
my several discussions with with john
raviki especially in
christian neoplatonism or also in
eastern philosophy like uh you can see
this in buddhism and also in modern
science the the solution to the prawn of
the one and the many and
which ends up being also a solution to
the uh combination problem in psychism
is sort of a combination of a worldview
that
is just emanation or just emergence and
you have to
identify both so rather
let's i can try to maybe go quickly
through
uh those two um a purely
emergentist worldview would be sort of a
just a bottom-up worldview and this has
several problems so a purely imagery
intestinal view would be
let's say you have fundamental particles
and then you have laws of physics that
govern those
and somehow complex things emerge from
the combination of those particles
and you know this has the
the advantage that you can sort of
understand the
different building blocks of things and
it seems to give you something really
solid but it has a huge problem that
it ends up making emergence sort of into
a miracle
like how is it that different things
could possibly
combine into something one like and
this point has been made powerfully by
different people
in in different ways one of the ways i
like to put it is
just consider two things spread in space
and time
something that uh in your it's an
example that in reverse and use
let's see how is it that two planets for
instance
they're separated that are separated in
space and time by thousands and
thousands of kilometers
how is it that they can interact with
one another that things that are
separate
can somehow uh relate how is it that
different things can somehow be won if
you just take sort of their individual
constituents
so that's a that's a problem if you want
to be just a purely
emergentist um you can look at more
complex examples like the fact that
somehow the human mind emerges from
matter
looks like a miracle if you're a purely
uh emanationist
but conversely if you try to take the
other way around of taking a
purely imminent worldview some
something like what the the neoclinist
did
you have just the opposite problem you
take the fact that okay well somehow
it's the it's the one it's the unity of
things that is primary
and there emanate multiplicity from it
so
to come back to let's see the example of
the planets it would be somehow like the
whole of the gravity
plus the planets that that exist that is
sort of
the source of it all and from this
emanates the differences between the two
planets and the space between them for
instance
but this sort of pure neoplatonism also
has issues because you know it's not
clear
why emanation would work you sort of
emanation ends up looking like a miracle
like why does the once amount decay into
the mini
and the solution that uh
has sort of emerged through my
discussions with
john is um is to combine both
if that's what the christian new
platoonists did that's also what
the i think buddhism is getting it and
it's what modern cognitive science are
good for i think
you have a a deep interpersonation of
both
emergence and emanation at the same time
uh we can look at the world
from both directions and we we sort of
don't get quite to the
whole picture but it's by identifying
both
we we end up with a reasonable system
so um in the case of the bright the
brain what seems to happen is that
both emergence and elimination are
perfectly
simultaneous there are two ways of
looking at the same
phenomena in let's say as i speak these
words for instance
if you were to look at my brain bottom
up
you would see all kinds of different
cells firing in all kinds of different
ways and
at some point if i'm into a certain
network and
somehow at some point you get
self-organizing criticality where
this this whole network will shift in a
extremely surprising way that looks kind
of miraculous where
just like once one one year run will
shift just a bit
in a way that will make the whole
network reconfigure extremely quickly
into one other network
uh into and if you were to look at your
in at the same thing going on top down
uh of how my my thought progresses
when i had a certain neural network
configuration i was thinking a certain
thought
and then i thought a different thought
and this corresponds to another neural
network configuration
and this shift that i look at at the
level of consciousness
is sort of one it's simple and at the
same time as this
abstract thought incarnates itself into
different neural networks
uh that's at as my thought emanates into
the the the many neural networks you
have it's simultaneous
an identical just a second a different
way of looking at the same thing you
have a simultaneous emergence of
the different neural networks with all
kinds of complexities
the emergence of all those into one
simple thought so
that's that's that's where i got
from taking the the stillman critique of
pensacon seriously
i got a further away from the modern
versions of pansenkism
that don't incorporate any neoplatonism
and i ended up
enriching my worldview because of this
all right great thanks thanks that was
that was a great answer
uh struck sean has a question uh so
we concocted a symbolic solution to the
zombie crisis
what do you make of it so here's here's
what they proposed
what is the problem with a zombie no
soul how do you install a zombie
soul food what's soul food mana
what is the philosophical philosophical
concept that attaches to mana
potential how do you save a zombie
confront them with their own
transactivity
because that reveals to the zombie their
own potential and through the exposure
they can no longer remain zombies
interesting i'll i'll have to re-read
this and think about it
what is the problem with a zombie no
soul
how do you end soul zombie soul food
what's soul food mana what's the
philosophical concept that
just added just to mana potential how do
you save a zombie
confront them with their own
transactivity because that reveals to
the zombie their own potential
and through the exposure they can no
longer remain zombies
i don't know i think i would name more
details i find it difficult to
imagine what this means exactly um
and i think students uh
mike or is anyone else here who who is
involved
there are a few people i think involved
with uh crafting that but i'm not sure
if
if they're online or maybe it's true and
you could you could
see if someone is around who has a mic
and who can come in and
and give give some some elaboration
uh so it's just it's especially the
first steps that i uh
i would like to see some argumentation
for uh
like when you go from i think i agree
with the first idea like what's the
problem with the zombie no soul
but then i'm not sure about the soul
food thing uh or the mana
or uh they move from mana to
to potential yeah but i do think there's
something
good about the move to to participation
uh to
transactivity because
and see i i've heard john say that the
solution to the meaning crisis is
building a meaningful
civilization and this goes in part with
transactivity with uh building
communities
where i do know that when i dealt with
the this issue symbolically with
jonathan
sir christianity goes a bit further
because you don't just try to build a
meaningful civilization but
you you also like try to save the
zombies even themselves
um so there
yeah and this does have to do something
with persuasion and transitivity because
in some sense you would have to do what
christ did we would have to
like somehow die for the zombies
i don't know how much this maps with uh
what you just drawn
i might be able to play with this a
little bit um
it might be slightly off off the point
of strawn but
um as far as like the uh how do you
insole a zombie
um and the answer being soul food it
i noticed that there seems to be a
parallel there to what you were bringing
up
earlier with the cell towers in that
seemingly the zombie is having a
a confusion of what the symbol
represents so right the question might
be
why do zombies eat flesh yeah yeah
that's good and it seems like
what they're trying to eat is that
they're trying to
insult themselves except that they've
confused the symbol of what a soul is
to being a body or being flesh or being
the brains right they eat brains
um so it does seem like there is
some aspect of of this kind of symbolic
confusion taking place where the zombie
is trying to find
uh that way to integrate the soul and is
confused in the way of
going about it yeah yeah yeah that's
that's a very good point uh
thank you what's your name by the way uh
nick oh thanks nick yeah i think that's
uh yeah that's very enlightening
yeah i agree that's yeah and this makes
the move to transactivity uh
clearer as well it's you can see the
move within uh
john's lecture series where from
a world view with the ancient greeks
where transactivity was
was accepted and played an important
role
to the modern self where we isolated
ourselves
more and more where we sort of became
trapped uh
within our own minds our own persons
where we cut ourselves up from
from the world from others and even from
ourselves from our own bodies
and the the zombie metaphor is very apt
in that
yeah as you said the the brain is
is a symbol for the mind is a symbol for
for meaning but the zombie it's
eats it just at the physical level you
can see it doesn't get
to the like the the social
the transactive nature of our souls
ah and then
i i'm not yeah so then i i would agree
with that move
uh that you have to confront the zombie
with like
a better symbol you have to show the
zombie that the
like the desire to eat the brain to eat
meaning is
starts from a good intuition that the
brain has something to do with meaning
but is misdirected and sort of falls
back to the physical layer of the brain
rather than looking out at how the brain
is a symbol that links
individual bodies to communities like
how it links you
as an individual physical person to
other people and that in this
relationship
you uh become mindful in that in that
relationship you become like a soul that
you develop your personality we won't
even have personalities without other
people we need
uh especially during infancy to be
confronted with others
for our uh minds to become
real for output for our personalities to
form
so i agree with that that we would need
somehow to recover this for the zombies
to confront them with
with transactivity uh i guess i would
yeah then my last question would be
about the potential which i'm not
yeah i guess i'm not sure how you would
even need the potential step
yeah and nick you had you had a question
of your own actually
uh yeah yeah it did um
yeah so i was wondering if you're
and you perhaps kind of answered this in
an earlier question um in the difference
between the
the emanation and the uh emergence
but i'll ask it anyways and see if it
helps
does your pan psychism lead to a
pantheon a more of a pant
uh pantheist view kind of in the sense
of spinoza
uh or a pan-enthist view and
if the latter do symbols have access to
that
aspect that extends beyond the creation
okay good question
i think i don't think that psychism
by itself entails uh either
dentism or panentheism
it has been common for pennsylvania
i mean both have been occurring in the
last century it was
it was a fairly common move when there
was sort of a first wave of fence like
about 100 years ago uh with arthur
eddington uh bertrand russell
uh henry bergson and some of them
uh yeah i should also mention uh uh
whited they were some of them were
quite fond of moving to a version of
pantheism or panama theism
but i don't think you have to
necessarily go that route
um you can also maintain that
okay so fantasm
explains how different consciousnesses
can can combine
how it is that when you have the let's
see the meeting of
emergence and emanation uh you get
something like
consciousness whether the meeting occurs
within a uh
a nucleus in a cell or whether it
happens uh in a mind
sorry whether that or whether it happens
in the head of a body or whether it
happens let's say in
in the the priest of a parish
you can see at this meeting of two
layers of being
you would get consciousness like somehow
that consciousness is what mediates
uh between those layers of being and
that symbols point to
conscious conscious things you you can
make that move not all and psychists
will do so
um recently especially the last
wave of uh pensacon most ten psychists
haven't made the move to even uh
higher than human level consciousness
most
and psychists today will say that okay
well i mean the there is consciousness
at the
level of fundamental particles and they
can combine into more and more complex
ones until you reach the human level but
after this it's sort of
finished so you can get this as well and
then
if i want to talk about the uh
pentheism or panentheism more directly
in terms of how
this fits within uh religions i think
it's
it's quite possible to say that
beyond all of this uh
emergence and elimination that we see
within the modern world
within the natural world there may be
still
some like a ground of being behind all
of this from which like
somehow both the emergence and the
emanation come from
so i don't think that uh consensus needs
to
entail either atheism or penetration you
see a broad array of views
um and i'd still like to answer the last
questions
two symbols have access to that aspect
that extends
beyond the the creation
and i think the answer for this is a is
yes
you'll find this in most spiritual
traditions
uh where you have a
you know in in buddhism it's the the
buddha in uh christianity it's christ
you have someone that
acts as a symbol to unite divinity and
humanity you know it's different between
buddhism and
uh christianity in christianity god is
is uh is personal and incarnates fully
in a person
that is man that is jesus christ where
in buddhism
it's the the non-being of of buddha it's
his participation as a man into
the non-being into the emptiness that
allows him to reach
from human to uh to divine but
in both systems you have a symbol that
unites
the created world you know a man in the
created world to
uh the uncreated to uh
what is beyond creation does it answer
the question nick
right yeah that's that's a good answer
and and just to clarify slightly i
i was um more curious about your
specific
um take on pan psychism then pan
psychism in general but
i take the point that from a purely
emergent perspective
uh you can very easily sidestep uh
either
pantheism or a panic okay okay oh but
i can try to answer better your question
then thank you
the way i like to see it is in within my
pen psychism
especially within christianity it's uh i
like to distinguish between
pentheism up and pantheism down
and i think pantheism down is a bad kind
of pantheism where you try to pull
divinity down to humanity uh
with your pantheism you try to just say
that okay well then
the totality of creation is god i don't
think that's a
i don't think that's a valid move
because it leaves you with all kinds of
questions that are actually quite clear
if you go back in philosophy to let's
say the
ancient greeks or the medieval medieval
philosophers
it doesn't answer the question of the
ground of of being it doesn't
answer the like the where do we just
creation come from
so but clearly you have within
either christianity or even within
buddhism the desire for a sort of
pantheism up
where creation is meant to participate
in god but doesn't quite do it and
creation will never
exhaust no matter what how well it
participates in god it will never like
fully express god but god is still
drawing creation
into himself so within christianity this
occurs with christ
who let's say he became a man and then
gathered people
died founded the church and then the
church has been expanding and in doing
so
the the ultimate purpose is for all of
creation to be united under the locals
under the divine principle
under christ so the goal is to raise
creation uh to god
so it's not a a
a naive pantheism that just identifies
creation with with god
it's rather a an aspiration for
creation to be united with god and you
get the same sort of thing in buddhism
where the buddha is supposed to draw
people into participation
to the ground of being which is
impersonal in that system but still the
goal is to draw creation
into uh into emptiness into non-being
right so would you would you say it's
fair to characterize that as
pan-enthism
i um well because it seems like you're
you're hinting towards something that is
beyond merely the creation
yeah i think yeah you will have to can
you give me your precise definition of
planning theism because
all of those terms are so fraught uh
with debates right now that i i'd like
to know precisely how you see it
i i guess with pananthism i'm i'm
thinking of
you know the i perhaps a classic idea
that god is fully present
within the creation but also extends
beyond it
so you see fully present in the system
um i said this gets closer
but yeah i would have to look more
precisely into the arguments
against this view because i know there
are lots of arguments against
uh i mean yeah there's lots of
opposition i should say rather than
arguments to this within
uh religious circles whether they be
uh eastern or western so i would yeah
i'd be more careful
and i wouldn't want to clearly say
panentheism
right right that's unfair yes absolutely
sorry i can't answer more precisely but
yeah that's just
a topic tyler
go ahead
oh i was just kind of being cheeky but
yeah i was just talking about self and
then
how strange the symbol of self is
because it
in what what girdle showed us i think in
in terms of
how logic is constructed or or how it is
that we can take a meta
analytical point of view it seems to
indicate that there's something
and then this is actually funnily enough
perhaps touching on the pain and
theistic element or the directionality
of this
transjective component but like pointing
to something
outside of the system that is
considering it or that is being under
consideration and so what then is that
symbol
if the symbol itself is potentially a
self
right like what what the hell is really
going on there
um and and maybe that's also tying in
with the compositional
aspect of of this right um hmm
that's interesting and i don't think i
quite get the cash the question so
me i can ask you to when you say that
the self is a symbol
um can what do you mean more precisely
what does the the self mediate uh
from into exactly the thing that
describes me
right okay yeah like that is when i when
i summon the symbol of self
it it summons this uh notion of a vessel
of a container that is
incorporating elements right it's this
um
perhaps the general organizing component
okay and can you remind me of the the
link you are trying to make
between that and the ground of being oh
sure yeah so if that
thing itself as it is being utilized
in the functioning of pulling that forth
right so that yeah this is the
self-referential aspect of it so
the physical process is in my brain here
are involved in
this this self-assessing
self-constructing
self whatever reference thing so that
they're what is it pointing to
right like that's that's i guess the
element but
and that's partly why it's cheeky i
suppose yeah but i guess i can try to
so i i tend to use the symbolism of the
head and the body but you can try to use
other
symbolic structures as well jonathan
really likes to use the center and the
periphery
and maybe i can try to use this to talk
about the the symbol of the self as you
describe it
uh maybe this can help us make some some
headway there
um seems to me like the way you describe
the self is
say it's maybe it's like the
what mediates between the world
or oh maybe it's what media between yeah
your world and your center
like you're you don't have a perfect
access to to yourself to your inner self
uh so you need a some intermediates you
need a way to get at it and to get at
your center
uh you use use the symbol of the self
which media is between like the world
you see and
your uh your deepest nature for instance
and
then you call this the self this makes
sense you think
yeah well yeah so that which mediates
potential into actuality
right and potential is the landscape of
possibility that is okay yeah
yeah yeah okay yeah yeah oh yeah then
that makes a lot of sense um
because then sort of the any self is
anything that does mediate between
potentiality and actuality
whenever you have a meeting of
potentiality and actuality you get
something you get
like a self you get an entity that
actually exists
um okay so i think i think that i think
that's fair
can you maybe try to restate your
question
using this yeah okay so we've just
discovered that component of it right so
like we've unfolded
but so that thing in itself is a self
right yes yes right yeah right so
whatever immediate between potential and
actuality
is itself yeah
yeah well okay but if it's so all right
so
it this i'm really just pointing to the
self-referential aspect of this the way
you get stuck um but i think that's
i think it's like fundamentally embedded
in the ground of being because that
is where it's paradoxical right it's
where you have to bottom out
and then from that place construct
interesting
and and and so yeah that's why it seems
that i
i would agree with you that that in this
way you get to a kind of
of pantheistic sense where
everything at the the base bottom layer
where you can't deconstruct it any
further
builds up from a place of kind of
impossible
paradox whatever it can and in the
potential
right and that's yeah so yeah yeah
yeah yeah i think i think that's good um
and you know in terms of of christianity
this is checked out in
you know the idea that that
the ground of being is is behind
both emergence and emanation
that somehow the ground of being by
being the
the source of the potent yeah the source
of the potential and the source of
the actual is to see beyond the self
like it's a
it's a it's a self uh i should say
beyond the self in that it's beyond
potential and actual that somehow
it's the origin and meeting of of both
so you sort of get to a sort of trinity
uh
yeah it just made me think of this i
think that's cool that was a good
question tyler
well it's a and it's a beautiful point
you just made there because i think
that's
really what christianity captures deeply
in the philosophy and the theologies
is is the the triality of things
that we end up at yeah it's really great
thank you it's really cool like somehow
there's this idea that
the let's say god god the father
only really is and you can see this in a
jonathan's conversation with uh
jonathan's last conversation with john
where they touched just a bit
on the nature of person and this had a
bit to do with the trinity
the idea that a a human being we can't
even really
be a human being until we have to face
let's see the the potential
of others we become a self when we we
actualize
within a network of the potential people
that's what we become a self and
this is reflected in the trinity in in
the idea that it's
what makes the father and the son and
the holy spirit
persons uh it's really the fact that
they interact with one another the fact
that somehow
the what is behind the emergence what is
behind the emanation
uh is is both uh
like this meeting of potential this
meeting of the ground of potential the
ground of the actual
is a relationship like if you only had
one of those they wouldn't really exist
like potential doesn't even really make
sense
without the actual you just sort of get
emptiness
and conversely the actual can truly
exist either unless it has potential to
actualize into so it wouldn't really
exist and
of course the meeting of both wouldn't
exist either you can't have
potential an actual meeting without
having both potential and actual so you
can get the trinity this way where you
you have a growing potential the ground
of the actual and the meeting of the two
yeah and i love the notion of
the the the community toss the spirit
that is invoked in
cooperative elements right because
because there isn't any real geometry
there
per se it is i mean think of
if if you you think of the component of
the flattening of that
of that connective tissue out across the
globe right and the
incredible way in which we're able to
orchestrate our activities together and
produce such
profound miraculous things in concert
together
that are highly abstract um it's
yeah it's truly a psycho technology
right
yeah yeah thanks tyler it was that was
cool we've got a little bit over do you
have time for
one or two more yeah yeah sure
i still have maybe 30 minutes okay great
so
uh strewn has a follow-up question why
not flip
the combinatorial problem in reverse why
not stipulate that it's an issue of
dividing consciousness
stipulating that space is the pan psyche
the formal cause
is a neat solution to james object
objection
yeah that's the solution that's so some
people have been trying and
it's a through the same thing that i
think the neoplanets were
trying to to get at um
but you sort of get the the inverse
problem it's called within pansenism
it's called
the decombination problem the idea of
how can then
one consciousness become several
consciousnesses
um and really the the objections
map onto uh the same thing so
it seems and i think this points to the
sort of
marriage between images and emanation
that i've been talking about here that
you can see in the christian new
blackness or in buddhism or in modern
community science
that if you get a real solution to the
combination problem
about different consciousness can
combine you get a simultaneous solution
to the the decombination problem to the
problem how different consciousness can
can divide like though both the
combination and the division
are deeply into penetrating and
inter-reporting
and i think this is what yeah that's
what john is getting at within cognitive
science it's what the christian neocons
were getting at 1500 years ago
uh and it's what i think also the
buddhists are according to all right
dana you have a question
or i can i can read it out uh
what what do you think of the interface
theory of perception
and and how that could relate to pan
psychism
a good question it's been a while since
i looked at uh don of man's work
precisely but i'll i'll do my best here
i think that don offman's work
is good to point out a problem if you
take his assumptions
but i think where he goes wrong is when
he instead of he gets to a strange
conclusion where
it turns out we have like no contact
with the world that we're
very wrong about almost everything and
rather than looking at his hypothesis
again and doubting them he just
takes that as a granted as go and goes
to a full-blown idealism
and i don't think that's quite warranted
if you if i remember correctly
if you look at the none of men's papers
what you'll see
is that it starts off with a
correspondence theory of no i should say
it starts off with a i think it's a
representational
theory of perception where okay you have
the world and then within our minds
we create representations of the world
and then from that
he then goes on to uh he adds a few more
hypotheses and then he makes uh
game theoretic simulations and also some
i think now he also has um actual like
probability uh demonstrations to show
that if you start with these hypotheses
you end up with the idea that the the
interfaces or you can say the the
representations that we have of the
external world
actually have to be radically wrong they
have to be radical over simplifications
that will not even be isomorphic to the
real world so
you will not it's not only that you will
sort of approximate the real world
according to him is that your like the
heuristics you end up with
will have to be not isomorphic to the
real world and an example uses is uh
this is like the trashcan on your uh
computer screen
it's nothing like what actually happens
when you delete
something in your laptop and that's the
conclusion he reaches that somehow
natural selection gave us a perception
that is
radically disconnected from what
actually goes on in the world
but i think this was almost bound to
happen from his uh
initial hypothesis and some philosophers
have been
disputing this for for a while the idea
that we represent the world
uh rather than just interact in contact
with it
i think there's something very let's see
maybe
like what the cat or count are doing uh
in hofmann i think it's nice that he
proves it mathematically
that if you start with the idea that we
represent the world
and that we're not in contact with it
then we end up with a radical separation
that's i think what happened from the
cap to count
but rather than going this way i think
you can do what the phenomenologist
did also what henry berkshire did and
you instead say that
well rather than us representing the
world we actually have
contact with the world at the this in
terms of john's uh
uh john system i think you would say
that we have um
error in one of the four p's the lowest
level the four piece was the i think
it's the participatory
right we can have participatory contact
with with reality and from this we can
build i o level perceptions
that become more and more abstract and
that have let's say
more and more chance of losing contact
with the world
uh but if you start this way
then you you do not agree with huffman's
uh
uh hypothesis that we represent the
world
rather you start with a contact and
because of this
you uh like do not have to endorse the
idealism
that um that huffman goes to
and to answer like the second part of
the question how could that relate to
ben sanchez well you can see that even
with what afman gets to
uh it gets through sort of idealism and
you can see idealism as a subset of the
psychism
it's a fantasm the idea that everything
as
as mind at to some level there are
asterisks of course but the idea that
at the final level everything is
conscious
uh huffman will get there the idealism
but there are other ways to be a pen
psychist and i don't think it's the most
convincing one i think the best
one is the is to see fan psychism as
within the framework of emergency
animation that we we discussed earlier
does that answer the question
he said yes thank you mr persona you
have a question
um hello can you hear me yeah i can hear
you
all right um in light of current events
i wanted to ask you about the symbolism
of statues
yeah yeah so i think i think that there
are symbols that mediate between
past and future to create a community
identity so
how worried should we be about this
attack on statues
yeah that's a good question i don't know
if you saw jonathan's video which posted
yesterday on this topic
uh yes i did i just wanted to hear a
little more about it
yeah but i i think i think he got it
right where
statues or physical artifacts that media
between us
and our past that media is between us
and our common story
and it's not the only physical artifacts
that do so you can like the flag
does the same thing or the white house
in america where
you have something that's physical that
when you look at it brings you in into
participation with your country with
uh your fellow people so it's
so if you break down these symbols you
break down
your participation uh into the community
so it's you know what it does
immediately is fragment people
and there's potential for something else
to re-emerge for new symbols to
emerge but of course it's a it's a a
time of chaos
uh not only good things will probably
emerge from this
so i mean i guess we should be worried
to some extent we should
keep our eyes open and try to see look
at the symbols that will
emerge try to get away from the bad ones
and try to foster the good ones
so i guess we should be worried uh
to the extent that we can if we
shouldn't be worried too much about
things that we have no control over i
think
like unless you're like uh maybe uh
unless you're in the high position of
authority there's no need to
focus too much on very large stuff that
you have no control over
but we should definitely keep our eyes
open and try to see
at the level that to the extent that we
can what are the good symbols that we
can foster
from all of this mess no that that's a
very cool idea i like that idea of
emerging possibilities thank you
thank you for the question mr president
let's
wonder jp what do you i'm quite partial
to integrated information theory which
is
i call it sort of pan psychic pan
psychic light
where not every particle is cautious but
particles when they're in the shape of
information that's in the shape
of the pattern of integrated information
that's when consciousness uh manifests
uh
yeah are you yeah
what are your thoughts on uh have you
looked into iit or
what are your thoughts on that yeah uh
it's another thing i looked at in the
past it's been a while so i don't know
if that has changed much
since i i looked at it from what i
remember you know it has the advantage
of
being a formal description of
a pen psychist theory so i think it's i
think it's good in that it allows
the psychists to to test at least some
of their uh hypotheses
so for instance i think they were able
within integrated information theory
to like predict uh yet
i don't think they have really predicted
anything new so far but at least they
can explain some things that we already
see
like they can um explain
why certain neural networks are
correlated with consciousness and some
others are not
and you know if you start with okay so
you start with a bunch of postulates
that
imply a form of pensacon as you said
it's not quite there's some sort of a
pentagon and and you pointed this out uh
correctly brett it's not the sort of
psychism that
starts really from the bottom down where
every particle is conscious but
somehow the information is is conscious
so
maybe like i think i think it goes quite
far down though so
for instance the fact that uh an
electron can have spin up or skin down
means that the electron
contains some information and because of
that i do think that it means that
they're
like the the electron is conscious
within uh integrated information theory
but i'm not sure i would have to look at
it it's been it's been a while
ah but the point is just that with their
with all of their hypotheses uh they're
uh postulates they can predict a bunch
of stuff it predicts when
pencilism among other things it can also
have real uh
testable hypothesis i don't think they
have like anything new
so far but the fact that they can
explain things that already exist i
think is encouraging it's good for
atheism to have some empirically
testable
uh uh uh predictions
so i i think it's one i i think that
other
formal and psychist theories will also
uh emerge over time
even uh we mentioned integr uh we
mentioned um
donald dunn offman's interface theory of
perception and that's another
formal rendering of pencilism it's an
idealism that is also a pen
uh cynicism and it anyway and i know
that they are
working on trying to get some
empirically
testable uh predictions from it so
i think those are like steps in the good
direction
you know of course there would be
philosophical things i would dispute in
both
iit and the interface theory of
perception
but still i'm quite happy to see that
people are developing empirically
testable
uh versions of pensacon
does that help brett yeah yeah excellent
well thank you so much jp this has been
this has been just a great great talk
yeah
and yeah thank you for the invitation
and thanks to everyone for participating
it was a it was a great experience yeah
thanks everyone for being here and uh
make sure everyone to log on to our
google calendar which you can find
linked in the pin
post in the announcements channel and
we've got all sorts of activities going
on
so you know every day we've got
different things going on and
we're adding more more and more so
please
please take a look and and and
be here for see what you're interested
in so again thank you jp that was
amazing
and thanks everyone for being here yeah
thanks everyone
bye